Hello viewers, hello. Uh,
today I will talk about the
network and networking.
My name is Phac. I'm from, uh,
Concordia University Ch-
in Chicago, um, working on my, uh, master
degree in computer science program right
now.
So, uh, in this video,
we will cover five thing in network
system.
First is we will go through the network
foundation,
the Internet,
and the network fu-fundamentals.
The second one is the network edge
and network core.
I will explain the difference between
them.
Number three is the communication
and network protocols.
So we will understand what
is the network protocols,
why protocols are necessary in a network
system.
Number four is understanding the network
performance, the major
factor that affect the network
performance.
You will know why we getting lag,
uh,
slow when we try to watching the videos on
YouTube or et cetera. And finally
is the network security.
Why security is essential in the modern
computer
networks. So first,
let's go to the network foundation.
As a definition,
we will have the computer network
is a group
of two or more computer
or devices that are connected, so they can
communicate and share resources such as
files,
printers, application, or Internet access.
In this one, we will--
There's another thing
when they talk why people
saying, like, network
is a network of networks.
Because Internet is the,
uh, ultimate network system, where
is the massive
global system made by joining from the
smaller and
independent computer network together.
Or you can say as the--
It's made of many separate computer
networks connect together around the
world, and also the way
that bi-billions of device
can communicate because of individual
networks are connected
together,
and routers use shared protocol
and address
to direct data packet to the correct
destination.
In the network, we will have two main,
uh, device or layers,
uh, that been used. One
is the end system or...
and the other one is a host.
So here we will have some example
for end system and host.
Here we have a laptop or, and desktop,
smartphone, tablet,
physical servers, cloud system,
or virtual machine,
or containers. So for a laptop,
it can be understand as a client or node,
and the network is
fully used, the,
to connect it
through the protocol wi-- uh, called TCP
or the stack of the IP through Wi-Fi
as a wireless connection, or Ethernet
is the physical connection
or wired connection.
The general purpose of it is the,
uh, co-computing,
web browsing, or local software execution.
Same as sm-smartphone or tablet,
but it can--
it's been called as a mobile client
because it's still
a full TCP/IP stack, but it's only
support for wireless connection like
cellular and Wi-Fi.
So with the purpose of that,
we can go on the media access,
app driving communication,
location services,
or you can easily understand
that you're using social media on your
phone.
Then we will have the host part
is the physical servers
or data center. With the purpose of that,
they using to host and
provider the services.
It's required the higher bandwidth
and heavily
used on network,
so it's normally connect with the fiber
interconnect to
keep the networking or the network, uh,
data transfer
be stabilized and safe.
Physical server can
dedicate as a compute engine hosting the
website, database,
and enterprise services. Next is the cloud
system or the virtual machine
that sit on the
s-physical servers where we
or the end user or the enterprise can
virtually hosting it.
The connection is using the
software-defined network, uh, uh,
called as the SDN.
So with the purpose of that, they used
to virtualize server instance running on
top of the physical
data center, center,
uh, infrastructure
or the physical being host locally.
So we will talk about some example of a
real world,
how the data, uh, can receiving
and transferring,
uh, through the Internet.
So just a fresh
understanding is the,
uh, router Wi-Fi, where it's been
sit on every single home now,
where you can connect wireless
for gaming, music, streaming,
uh, email, et cetera.
Then we will have the, uh,
station for cellular,
where you can have the 5G
or 6G signal in the long
range. You,
you don't have to worry about the
connection.
And then we will have the Ethernet
or the fiber
connection.
It's like a cable insert in your
router or under the network system,
where
it's more stable and the high bandwidth,
and you don't have to share the bandwidth
with the other
when you access or using the fiber
or Ethernet signal.
And then that's all for the, uh,
foundation for
understanding the basic of the
network.
And now we go to the network edge
and the network
core.
So for the network edge,
as we talk about the host
and an end system,
so we will-- in the network edge,
it will call
as the client and server.
And the definition of the network edge
is the part
of the network architecture where user
and end devices interface with the
internet.
It is decentralized, diverse,
and focused on
access and local service.
So there is flit- split in two
is client server.
So for the clients, the device
is normally,
uh, claim as request information
or update information
to the server. For example, a laptop,
smartphone, PC, wireless tablet,
IoT devices. Example of the action
is normally you do the
web browsing, go on the social media,
upload the
post, or update the, your information.
For the server,
it's require more powerful to
handling multi connection in one server.
So the power of machine
that able to store and provide
service to the clients
while many server live in a massive
data center deep within the network core.
For example, the web server, datas-
database servers,
application server. The other rule of
that is the hosting on AWS,
where you can put your code on or the,
or the
website on, and then it will host.
So many other people can
go in yours or GitHub, where you can
GitHub,
and they will have their Git server to
store all of the code
base. Then
now we have to talk about the access
networks.
An access network is the physical link
that connect a
host to the first router,
also known as the edge
router of the ISP network. The ne-
access network is often
the bottleneck in term of the bandwidth.
So why we can call it as the
bottleneck? Because it's the very end
before it's connect to your laptop or...
So for the home network, we will--
they will provide the internet
access within the, for the resident
and normally used as the home router
or the modem Wi-Fi access for the either
way
combined to the one thing with all
purpose.
For the enterprise,
it's the network connect user within a
company
or a university setting.
Ethernet sw- it have the Ethernet switch,
wireless access
point,
enterprise-grade firewall,
and internal server.
So this can provide all of the local
devices or any
local devices before it go through the
network core,
go in the network core.
And finally, it's a mobile.
It's using for wide range network,
use cellular technology to
provide the wireless access over large
area,
4G or 5G radio access network, and mobile
devices.
Then we will talk about the network core.
It's the Internet backbone where
s- single, uh,
network core connecting together create
the huge system of the network layers from
country to
countries, city to cities.
Yeah. The network core
is the backbone of the Internet.
It's all purpose to provide the high
speed, reliable transport
of data packets over long distance,
connecting many different access networks
together. So in the network core, you will
have the single part
that using for different
purposes. We have the routers
or core routers.
It's made to specialize in high-capacity
router that
interconnect standard access network
and other
ISPs.
They focus on the router packet between
different networks
rather than connecting directly,
directly to end device.
Switch is the core switch. It's m- able to
handling large amount and higher,
uh, bandwidth.
So it's a high-performance switch
used within the data center
or between the router to
manage the high-speed physical connection.
The physical medium connecting these
device, primarily
high-capacity fiber optic cable.
So you can understand as the network core
is like a server,
but shipping station
that collecting all of the
shipping from your home,
transfer it to the designate,
uh,
address that you're already assigned for.
So to understand more in the network,
it's not only about the network edge
or core, it's
also, uh,
packet or data been traveling through
the network.
We will have to know about the,
uh, packet traveling method,
where the data transferring
through from your devices to, um,
designate
server or through all of the network
system.
So we have, uh, four thing.
Packet switching is
one of the method, is the data
is gonna be broken down into
small or discrete block called packets.
Each packet contain destination address
in its header.
The router examine the header
f- of each packet independently to
determine the best outgoing link.
So the data, like for your photos,
when you're sending
to your friend,
it's not transferring the whole thing
Right away, it's break down
to small piece and each piece connect
together and it's go the same, or
the, the go to the same address. Uh,
so the internet is
the no dedicated path or,
or reserve bandwidth.
So the packet switching
is used by the internet,
no dedicated path and
or reserve bandwidth.
The bandwidth is used on-demand
statistical
multiplexing. This is more efficient
for perceived traffic
and such as web browsing or email.
Because we're using the public network
system, so
there's multiple connection happening in
the network
system. So,
and you will have multiple route
or multiple way to get into your, uh,
address.
Will have used to based on demand, and
we will
let you know where
this way is full of traffic or not.
And then is the other way of
method is the circuit switching.
A dedicated
end-to-end path,
uh, is ex-established between the
sender and receiver before any data
transmitted.
So this method is been used by the legacy
telephone network.
So the bandwidth is reserved exclusively
for that
connection and its entire duration.
While this guarantees performance,
it is highly in-efficient
if the connection
is idle. So the,
the difference between two is one
is for breaking down data
and one for reserving one way only
for the consistent data transferring.
So now we're gonna go to show the diagram
of the network edge and the network
core. So here you can see is a diagram,
gram
of the network edge.
We will use the home access network as a
sample
to easily to understand and visualize,
'cause
everyone will have it.
So the home router will
handling all everything.
It will providing the Ethernet.
Uh, it will connect with your PC
or desktop through Ethernet
or Wi-Fi, and laptop with Wi-Fi
or Ethernet, and then your
smartphone will have a Wi-Fi router for
it.
And the network printer,
you have Wi-Fi and IoT, like smart
thermostat or the cameras will, will,
will be
connect in,
connecting together through your home
router.
And from the home router,
you have the Ethernet connection through
the modem DSL
cable or coax phone line. It will
send...
These three will connecting together to
the ISP edge router,
which will connect to the c-network
core in your local area.
And then the local area
will send with the other network core in
the different area b-based on
the connection. And so this is the, uh,
basic
diagram to understand how the connection
between,
uh, the end device or loc--
or home device connecting
together. And then we gonna do to show the
network core.
So for the network core, after sending,
for example, you
have the laptop here,
you sending the message to your
friend. It's going through the net-
your home network
access first,
and then go through the network core where
the
ISP,
ISP network. It will handling all of the,
uh, sending through all the core router A,
sending
to B if it's closer,
or sending through the, uh,
application server where you under--
where you can
know all this one,
sending through the social media
and the cloud
storage or the database server to store
the,
your message,
and then send back again to update
on your screen and send another to your
friend. So this
core router, if you know,
is you can see is connecting together
A to B, B to C,
or s- or different l- different way,
but it will,
uh, locating or understand is, as, uh,
you can multiply it,
or hundreds of that or millions of
that in surround the world.
Now we're going back to the communication
and network,
uh, protocol.
So we have known the diagram
and layers of the network,
uh,
that have been used in the network system,
and but we don't know how it communicate,
communicate
to each other and how they understand
where to go and,
and what way for the efficient
and correct path
for it. So in the network protocol,
as the d-definition,
is the agreed-upon set of
rules, format, and convention that govern
how data is formatted, transmitted,
routed, received
across interconnected system,
including your home
devices.
So we will have, uh,
the HTTP or HTTPS
is the purpose of define how message
format and
transmit it for the fetching the web
resource.
And, uh, the layers of that
is they operate at
the application layer.
Then is the TCP to
p-provide the reliable order
and error check
gu- the delivery of, of a stream or
offset
between the application running on host.
The layer
of that is they operated at the transport
layer.
Then the IP
Address, the pur is responsible for
addressing the node
and routing discrete data
packet and operate at the network layer.
And DNS is the translation,
the human readable into the
machine routable IP address, and it's, uh,
operated
at the application. Later on,
where I will show the example of
these four interacting,
but now we're gonna go next to
the diagram to understand the purpose
and the layer
that we already mentioned from above.
So this layer is the, can understand as
the OSI layers, where you can go from the
physical is the, of the device,
physical device
that been used in a network system like
fiber, link, switch,
router,
uh,
uh, cellular station or et cetera.
And then the data link
is a physical addressing
and a network and a path de-determination.
And then they, they go into the transport,
reliable data transferring,
managing
connection,
and presentation,
the data translation befr-
right before the
application used to show the visualize.
And we will have eight different network
protocols
to, and purpose,
with the purpose to transferring
data.
Um, we have HTTP, HTTPS,
WebSocket, TCP, UDP, SMTP, and FTP.
Each of the connection have a different
purpose and, uh, different advantage.
We have showed a diagram,
so now we're gonna go to sample real
interact,
explain how server protocol work together
to make the activity possible.
So here I will,
I will inspect this one
in order to
search and do order.
[keyboard clacking]
So we let's see,
uh, network.
It's where you're sending out the data
to search on web browsing. So
after we send a network,
you will see here m- multiple
fetching from the data, from the server.
Uh, we will have to
see,
uh, payload, respond, initiator,
review.
So you can see here where the code
implemen-
uh, implement. That's where the
translator, the data translation do
when we
receiving the connection.
[keyboard clacking]
And from the network,
let me take a look for the API call.
So the API call the, the DNS.
The DNS is the Google lead or YouTube,
et cetera, and getting the link out here.
Um,
it's the easy to understand, but however,
in the foreign people to read, but for,
for, uh,
computer is a different way.
So we're gonna do
[keyboard clacking]
Google IP address.
So you can see here the Google IP address
is A
eight.
So if you searching for a
google.com...
Wait, hold on.
It will call as the,
call the API to get the data,
but it's transferring in the remote access
is the IP address here.
And we will...
And each of protocol accepting the,
the
searching the DNS,
like a Google to transferring to the
IP address, and then the TCP will
getting back,
sending out back to all of the, uh,
packet that need to rendering the,
rendering the web page
or web browsing to visualize
for end user
working.
So this is a sample of that.
So next, we're gonna w- talking about the,
um,
number four is understanding about the
network performance.
So there's many factor
that affect the network performance.
First is the throughput,
where the actual rate of data successfully
deliver,
deliver over the network path per unit
of time. The bandwidth is the theore-
theoretical
maximum data carrying capacity of the
network link and
measured in bit per second.
Delay the total time required for the
data packet to travel from source node to
the,
to its destination. Number four,
transmission data, the time required
to push all bit of packet onto the
physical transmission medium
And queuing de-delay
is the time packet spending,
spend waiting in a router
or switch queue buffer
prior to being processed
and transmitted. And final
is a packet loss, the
percentage or,
or ratio of transmitting mit--
transmitted data packet
that failed to reach their
destination.
Now we're gonna show
back to the diagram,
where
you will see.
So the data been transferring, um, around,
so
they will have some delay because of the
distance, the bandwidth and
the,
uh, the traffic.
So let's first go for the,
the bandwidth or the current network.
So we will showing up
the
network
speed test.
So this is an easy way to do,
as you can see here, the megabits
per second is five or through 500.
It's because I'm
currently on school,
and we have a really great, uh,
router that's sending out device.
So you can see here is the,
the theory or the currents
after calculating for the data to
transferring,
to download and upload in the same second
per, uh, per second,
the megabit per second.
And next is the latency, is the ping
or delay, uh,
between sending the data is four
millisecond. The server location
is Chicago.
And we will try on ping. Okay?
So
here
we will have to ping. For example,
we know that the eight--
eight eight is Google,
so we try to ping from our location.
So this is how to... How we can know that
reply in thirty-two byte of data.
It take three
second
to transferring data,
and we're sending out four, receive four,
and there's no loss.
There's no loss percent in here.
And the min-minimum and maximum ping, the
delay we have is three second,
three millisecond.
Maybe my, uh, application don't have it,
but it's fine.
But we can go to
Wireshark.
It's another tool in
checking the network system.
It takes some time. It's my first time.
So let's see.
So you can see here the data has been
flowing, so
it's kinda a lot.
So we'll see the protocol,
what protocol have been used through
the Wi-Fi
and the, uh, source from we receive the IP
address in IPv6 or IPv4,
and the destination
that we send our receiving.
So at the bottom here is the packet
that been sending
out in data,
and it's breaking down through line.
Each line is the one packet.
And
you will see that we have a series of line
that been sending.
Yep.
So that's a good,
uh... We stop it quick.
So this example how we, uh, looking up the
data transferring,
and we can see the delay through,
uh, using speed test
or testing our connection,
uh,
testing our connection.
So let me see if I can ping some
unreal connection.
We can use this, uh,
pinging the data transferring.
Request timed out.
We try to ping the unreal
connection.
So if the connection cannot going through,
and they try all the way
to sending our data up or packet out to
get that, the destination, we will...
If it's not connect to the,
the network system or the
general network sy- uh,
public general network system,
it will return
the packet been sent
and
forward but lost all four because there no
destination happen.
Okay.
Then,
and finally,
we going to the network security.
So in the security concept, we have, uh,
six thing, is authentication,
encryption.
For authentication
is the process of verifying the
id-identity of a user,
device,
or process before granting network access.
Encryption, the
mathe-math-ma-mat-mathematical,
mathematical process of encoding plain
text into the
ciphertext using cryptographic
key. Confidentially, confidentiality,
a fundamental s-pillar of security Triad
that ensure the sensitive data is
accessible only to the authorized
entities.
Network threat any potential
vulnerability or
deliberate
malicious action aimed at
disrupting operations, stealing data, or
gaining unauthorized access to network
resource.
IP
snooping,
a technique where an attacker alter the
source
address in IP packet header
to masquerade as the address network
entity.
Packet sniffing act the capturing and
analyzing raw data packet traveling across
a
network using packet analysis tool.
So for the authentication
and encryption is the connection where you
can SSH,
use for SSH connecting by,
for example, GitHub
is the one example for SSH
connection.
You put the public key on there
and they will do the
encryption to verify your authenticate to
connect the
link the server of GitHub from your
GitHub server to your local GitHub.
So you can able to transferring data
easier.
Authentication
is logging, so you can
log in
or
off. You can understand like a second
step of authenticate.
You need to put the number in or the
password and username to verify
that you are
connect to the,
that you verify to connect to the
services. If not,
you will check otherwise and
it will send out the key so you can keep
it while you're using it.
Then we will talk about the
network threat.
You will see some stealing data that
from the
Gmail or scam message where they sending
out data
that have a unreal thing
or they will have a link where
they can fake the website,
make you to log in and
they can get the access
by the mistake that you're typing out.
IP snooping or packet sniffing
is the same as
the way that I show on the
Wireshark where you can see all the data
transferring
in your local or on the network router
around and then you can from there you can
bring back the,
translate back the data
that been shared or sent
through the unsecure
protocol.
So how we can defend the network
security that it was the purpose of the
protect your
data and preserve system availability and
shield the sensitive information from
unauthorized access.
So we will have many layers
to against the
hackers or the one
that want to get your private
information. First is a firewall.
Firewalls is the
perimeter control
and filtering inspect incoming and
outgoing network traffic based on the
predefined security rules to block the
unauthorized connection and
malicious protocol.
Next is the virtual private
network. VPNs is the encrypted tunneling
establish and encrypt point-to-point
connection
over public network masking
IP address and protecting data from packet
sniffing.
And HTTPS or TLS
encryption is the transport layer
protection encrypts HTTP
communication between web browsers
and servers
using transport layer security TLS
in
mitigating the
eavesdropping
and man-in-the-middle attacks.
So we will after knowing about all
the way of protecting yourself.
So
the firewall is more
than easy to understand. The firewall
is more like gate.
You let
what
connection in, what out and you ban which
kind of protocol or the address.
For the VPN is more like you create like
your own way,
the private way from the public
network and then that's
against the
data sniffing or packet sniffing from the
others. For the HTTPS
is more likely the connection
been secure and it will encrypt all data
while
transferring on the network system.
So we will do the real example.
So scenario is consider a corporate
employee connecting to
the
an encrypted public Wi-Fi network at the
air- at an
airport. So from the public Wi-Fi
and unencrypted,
then attacker on the same Wi-Fi
network launch the packet sniffing tool to
capture local
airwave traffic. The attacker can
simulate-
simultaneously use the IP address sniffing
and
the ARP cache poisoning to position
themselves between the employee's laptop
and the
router, executing a man-in-the-middle
MITM attack, where, like, they create a s-
uh, middle
gate to collect all of the data that's
been
transferring through the router
and
get,
get all of your private information,
like login from the,
hmm, from your corporate,
your username, your password,
what you're doing, what you're
searching,
all of that. So the risk of that
is the employee access
internal com-company application via
unencrypted
HTTP. The attacker can intercept
the session cookies
and log in right away to credential in a
clear text. So you technically,
you give a key to
the attacker and open the gate to get all
of your money
out.
So the mitigation is to by enforce the
HTTPS
and routing all laptop traffic through a
VPN.
The transmission is encrypted end-to-end.
Even though the attacker capture the
physical packet via sniffing,
the payload appears as
unreadable and ciphertext
preserving the confidentially
and maintaining
the network integrity. So you apply the
VPN on that, and it creates a tunnel way,
and it's
encrypted your way.
So even though data can be
insecure and transferring on the Wi-Fi,
but they not able to
know what kind of data been sent out.
And yeah, that's it for the, uh,
network system that we have talked about.
After five thing,
uh, here's the reference
that I haven't used for the network.
And also, I using the,
uh, support in summarizing and, uh,
checking the
information accuracy and rephrase term,
so it's
more easier to read
and understanding as a common way.
Thank you very much.